<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Algernoon Sidneys farewel</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26660</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A923</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9251</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12713645</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12713645</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66128</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26660)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66128)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 372:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Algernoon Sidneys farewel</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet (2 p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. Davis ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1687]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sidney, Algernon, 1622-1683 --  Poetry.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:66128:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:66128:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Algernoon Sidneys FAREWEL.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WElcome, kind Death, my long tired Spirit bear,</l>
               <l>From hated Monarchies deteſted Air:</l>
               <l>And Waft me ſafe to th' happier <hi>Stygian</hi> Land,</l>
               <l>Where my dear Friends with flaming Chaplets ſtand:</l>
               <l>And Seat me high at <hi>Shaftsburys</hi> Right Hand.</l>
               <l>There Worſhipping, my Proſtrate Soul ſhall fall:</l>
               <l>Oh! for a Temple, Statues, Altars, all.</l>
               <l>Volumes, and Leaves of Braſs; whole Books of Fame!</l>
               <l>For all are due to that immortal Name.</l>
               <l>For my Reception then, great Shades, make room,</l>
               <l>For <hi>SIDNEY</hi> does with Loads of Honour come.</l>
               <l>No braver Champion, nor a bolder Son</l>
               <l>Of Thunder, ever grac'd your burning Throne.</l>
               <l>Survey me, mighty Prince of Darkneſs, round:</l>
               <l>View my Hack'd Limbs, each honourable Wound.</l>
               <l>The Pride and Glory of my numerous Scars</l>
               <l>In Hell's beſt Cauſe the old republick Wars.</l>
               <l>Behold the rich Grey Heirs your <hi>SIDNEY</hi> brings,</l>
               <l>Made Silver all in the Purſuit of Kings,</l>
               <l>Think of the Royal Martyr, and behold</l>
               <l>This bold Right Hand, This Cyclops Arm of Old,</l>
               <l>That labour'd long, ſtood Blood and Wars rough ſhock</l>
               <l>To Forge the Ax, and Hew the fatal Block.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nor ſtopt we here; our dear Revenge ſtill kept,</l>
               <l>A Spark that in the Fathers Aſhes ſlept,</l>
               <l>To break as fiercely in a ſecond Flame,</l>
               <l>Againſt the Son, the Heir, the Race, the Name.</l>
               <l>Revenge is God-like, of that deathleſs Mold,</l>
               <l>From Generation does to Generation hold.</l>
               <l>Let dull Religion and Sophiſtick Rules</l>
               <l>Of Chriſtian Ignorants, Conſciencious Fools,</l>
               <l>With falſe Alarms of Heavens forbidding Laws,</l>
               <l>Blaſt the Renown of our Illuſtrious Cauſe:</l>
               <l>A Cauſe, (what e're dull Preaching Dotards prate)</l>
               <l>Whoſe only Fault was being unfortunate.</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:66128:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Oh the bleſt Structure! Oh the charming Toyle!</l>
               <l>Had not Heav'ns Envy cruſht the riſing Pile,</l>
               <l>To what Prodigious Heights had we built on!</l>
               <l>So Babells Tower had <hi>Solomons</hi> Church out-ſhone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>True! my unhappy Blood's untimely ſpilt;</l>
               <l>And ſome ſoft Fools may tremble at the Guilt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As if the poor Vice-gerent of a God</l>
               <l>Were that big Name that our Ambition awd.</l>
               <l>A poor Crown'd Head, and Heav'ns Anointed! No!</l>
               <l>We ſtop at nought that Souls reſolved dare do.</l>
               <l>And only curſe the Weak and Failing Blow.</l>
               <l>Whilſt like the Roman <hi>Scaevola</hi> we ſtand,</l>
               <l>And Burn the <hi>Miſſing</hi> not the <hi>Acting</hi> Hand.</l>
               <l>Nay the great Work of Ruin to fullfill</l>
               <l>All Arts, all Means, all Hands are Sacred ſtill.</l>
               <l>No Play too foul to win the Glorious Game:</l>
               <l>Witneſs the great Immortal <hi>Teckleys</hi> Fame.</l>
               <l>In holy Warrs 'tis all <hi>True Proteſtant</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Kings to dethrone, and Empires to ſupplant.</l>
               <l>Nay and the Antichriſtian THRONE to ſhake,</l>
               <l>Curſt Monarchy, 'tis Famous even to make</l>
               <l>The <hi>Alcoran</hi> the <hi>Bibles</hi> Cauſe aſſume:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Mahomet</hi> the Prop of <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Such Aid ſuch Helps ſublime Rebellion wants,</l>
               <l>Rebellion the great <hi>Shibboleth</hi> of Saints;</l>
               <l>Which current ſtamp to <hi>Reformation</hi> brings.</l>
               <l>For all is [GOD with US] that ſtrikes at Kings.</l>
               <l>Now <hi>Charon,</hi> Land me on th' Elyſian Coaſt,</l>
               <l>With all the Rites of a Deſcending Ghoſt.</l>
               <l>A Stouter, Hardier Murmurer ne're fell</l>
               <l>Since the old Days of Stiff-neckt <hi>Iſrael:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Since the cleft Earth in her expanded Womb</l>
               <l>Oped a Broad Gulph for Mighty <hi>Corahs</hi> Tomb.</l>
               <l>Methinks I ſaw him, ſaw the yawning Deep.</l>
               <l>Oh! 'twas a Bold Deſcent, a wondrous Leap!</l>
               <l>More ſwift the pointed Lightning never fell.</l>
               <l>One plunge at once t' his Death, his Grave, his Hell.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>London, <hi>Printed for</hi> W. Davis <hi>in</hi> Amen-Corner.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:66128:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
